Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 8 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 December-1786 Mss.B.F85inventory08
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 April 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Barclay, David. London
    Introducing his two nephews, Daniel Bell and David Barclay; glad of this opportunity to gain some information of Franklin's welfare. Effect on people's health of the long winter and late spring.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 April 21; A.L.S. 4p.; Duché, Jacob Jr. Asylum, Lambeth
    Concerning the case of the eldest daughter of Mr. George Meade of Philadelphia, who has been unsuccessfully treated by the best physicians at home and in England for a complaint of the epileptic kind; her father's desire that she should be put under the direction of a M. Ledru (known in England as Comus) who has published an account of extraordinary curves by means of electricity; desires Franklin's advice concerning this new Parisian experiment, before the young lady undertakes the journey. Expects his father to join him in England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 April 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Johonnot, Samuel Cooper. Boston
    Account of his disagreeable voyage and his arrival in Boston, too late however to see his grandfather; acknowledging his faults in the past and his hopes for the future; left enough money by his grandfather to complete his education and enter the bar. Messages to Ben[jamin Franklin Bache].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 April 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Cadet de Vaux, Antoine-Alexis
    Forwarding the proof of the letter kindly sent him by Franklin; begs him to send it to the Journal de Paris before 9 o'clock Sunday, so that it may appear in Monday's edition. The Indian flour has arrived.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 April 25; A.L.S. 6p.; La Pierre, Dalzan de
    His reasons for desiring to live in America; the attraction for him of political, civil and religious liberty; desires to know what he may expect and what resources he may find there, refers Franklin to the Comte de Nozières for any information about himself; wishes his opinion about the desirability of settling in South Carolina, on the Pedee river.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 April 25; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Fisher, -----
    About to set out for London; offers to carry letters or messages to any of Franklin's friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 April 26; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Poissonnier, Pierre. Paris
    Writes on behalf of Messrs. Le Roy, Bailly and Lavoisier to ask if Franklin will receive them for dinner on Wednesday, together with the four Commissioners of the Royal Academy of Sciences; the object of the meeting is to discuss the plan to be followed in the inquiry into M. [Charles] Deslon's methods.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 April 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Stouppe, Pierre Louis. Ach
    Wishes a position in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1784. April ?]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Schaffer, John. Paris
    Acknowledging his kindness and protection; leaves Paris the next day.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779] May 3; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Wishes to have a private conversation with Franklin about some of her personal affairs.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Nov., 1906, p. 171.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Barrett, James. Bordeaux
    Has obtained a passage to America from one of the owners of a ship belonging to Ireland; informed by the Captain that on arrival he has to give security to the Chief Magistrate that all the passengers on board have an independence; appeals to Franklin for the truth of this.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Lefebvre d'Abancourt, -----
    Begging Franklin to hasten the return of three bills sent to his banker in March.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 6; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bailly, Jean Sylvain
    Difficulties in the way of Franklin's having all the Commissioners for dinner on Saturday; their desire to wait upon him Saturday afternoon, at which time a date might be arranged for the dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1784.] May 6; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bailly, Jean Sylvain
    Naming a day when the Commissioners appointed to inquire into "Animal Magnetism," may see and confer with Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 6; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Simon, ----- de
    Sends him a box and a packet which arrived in a case received from Mr. Benjamin Vaughan.
  - The Ministers Plenipotentiary of the United States., 1784 May 7, May 11, June 3; D.S. 13p.; The Continental Congress
    Instruction for negotiating treaties of amity and commerce.
    (Press copy.)
    Printed in the Secret Journals of Congress, III, 484-489, 493-497, 510-511.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779] May 8; A.L. 3p.; Brillon, Mme
    Telling of the trouble and sorrow caused by the actions of Mlle, J. whom she had befriended and taken into her home and who supplanted her in her husband's affection by intrigue and deceit.
    Printed in Purnam's Monthly, Nov., 1906, 171.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Percival, Dr. Thomas. Manchester
    Requesting Franklin's acceptance of his book "Moral and Literary Dissertations," just published. Changes in England since Franklin left; death of Sir John Pringle; establishment of a very useful Literary and Philosophical Society in Manchester. Letter received from Mr. Vaughan, containing some curious observations on cold made by Professor Patrick Wilson at Glasgow.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 11.; A.L.S. 3p.; Bridgen, Edward
    Delivered to Col. [Josiah] Harmar three rolls and one parcel; reasons for his delay in sending them; question of other commissions. Recommends "The Origin and Progress of Writing" by Mr. [Thomas] Astle. Expressing keen appreciation of Frankin's interest in his affairs in North Carolina. Messages from "his poor Patty."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Bridgen, Edward
    Recommending the bearer to Franklin's kindness. Desires to know the prospect of proceeding on the copper coinage. Asks Franklin's interest and attention to Mr. Parker's request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 11.; L.S. 1p.; Hopkins, Stephen. Providence
    Introducing Mr. Solomon Drown, who goes to France in order to perfect his knowledge in the healing art and in the French language.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 11.; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Feriet, ---- baron de
    The directors of the manufactory of St. Cloud have agreed to make all the glasses for the Harmonica; begs Franklin to step in during the day to contribute to the perfecting of the work and to judge of the methods proposed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Rayneval, Joseph Gérard de
    Introducing M. Chateaufort who is about to leave for America in the capacity of French Consul-General at Charleston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 15.; A.L.S. 1p.; Drummond, baronne de
    Begging for some assistance with which to meet the demands of her lawyer; has no other fortune than a great name; trusts him to burn her letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 15.; A.L.S. 1p.; Laubarède, ----- de
    Begs for a few louis to relieve his terrible suffering; refers Franklin to the Dutch Ambassador, M. Armand, for proof of his unhappy state.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Pintard, John Marsden. Madeira
    Enclosing an introductory letter from his uncle, Elias Boudinot, since which has received the appointment of Commercial Agent to the Island of Madeira and Porto Santo; if he can be useful in this capacity, begs Franklin to command him. Death of Mr. John Searle, Sr., will make no difference in the firm of that name; begs Franklin to recommend that house to any French company doing trade with the East.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Chevalier, -----. Paris
    Concerning some work ordered from him in 1777 by M. Feutry, an engineer, who promised him prompt payment in Franklin's name; encloses his bill and begs for a settlement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Saimier, -----. Paris
    Enclosing a letter in English [2p.] from John Gardner, Captain of the ship "Amity," and one in French [2p.] from M. Pierre Texier, merchant at Bordeaux; both documents concern the question of an unjust fine levied on part of the cargo of the ship "Amity"; informs Franklin that the affair has been practically arranged, with the exception of a nominal fine to be paid by Capt. Gardner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 18; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bebiniere, Gaspard de
    Begs Franklin to be present in the garden of the Tuileries at five o'clock, to witness an exhibition he will give of a new kind of pump, an invention of his own, which produces a quart of water in twenty-five seconds.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Pierres, Philippe Denis
    Begging Franklin to permit M. Baradelle to examine and make drawings of his small printing press, with an eye to simplifying the great number of French presses.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Renaux, A.T. Paris
    Desires to become an American subject; has two great draw-backs; his ignorance of English and his lack of a fixed income; desires to know in what capacity he may best render himself useful.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Drummond, baronne de
    Begs Franklin to befriend her as a woman of rank and as one of his unfortunate compatriots.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 23; A.L.S. 4p.; Young, Matthew. Trinity College, Dublin
    Has sent Franklin his treatise, lately published, on Sir Isaac Newton's theory of the pulses of air. At one time be entertained, wiht several others, the plan of establishing a college in America, which was abandoned upon the outbreak of the war; still desires to be useful to America in some capacity; is a fellow of the University of Dublin with a salary of £600 a year; begs for Franklin's advice and urges the need of secrecy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Regnier, Jerome. Tourcelles near Vouziers
    Begging Franklin to forward the enclosed letter to his son, Pierre Regnier, Colonel's equerry in the American army and also the first Frenchman who took arms for the defense of those "islanders."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 24; A.L.S. 4p.; Hopkinson, Francis. Philadelphia
    The new French Encyclopédic. Attempt he has made to raise the [American] Philosophical Society from a state of lethargy; aided in this by [David] Rittenhouse and Mr. Vaughan, Reforms needed in the education of youth. Encloses a little publication of his in reference to the cleaning of the streets. Experiments with balloons.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 90).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 24; Dr. of L. in 3d P. 4p.; Cadillac, Marie Therèse de Lamothe. London
    Concerning a large estate in America granted to her grandfather by Louis XIV; on being recalled to France he was forced to abandon these estates; her father died without seeing America; her own marriage to the noble Barthélemy de Gregoire and her present residence in London where she hoped to be put in possession of these estates; has just ascertained that by the latest treaty, her lands are included in the domains of Boston; their wish to avoid the expense of a trip to America; begs Franklin to put her in a position to obtain her rights.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 25; A.L.S. 4p.; Roulhac, -----. Limoges
    Begs for information concerning two of his brothers; one, who left France in 1777 and was last heard from in May 1781 as married and settled near Bath; and the other, a younger one, who went out to join him in 1782, and whose last letter reached them from Baltimore before his meeting with his brother; fears they may have been led into some wrong-doing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Valazé, Charles Eléonor Dufriche de
    Desiring to know if his manuscript was forwarded to Congress at the same time with his book; if only the latter was sent, will feel certain that the paper ought never to have seen the day.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Bassi, Anton-Benedetto. Paris
    Describes himself as a pupil of Père Beccaria, and as an unfortunate man of letters whose present illness has prevented his accomplishing an important literary work; begs assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 27; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Hunter, Dr. Paris
    Packet sent to Mr. [John] Jay at Paris by Dr. [John] Witherspoon, who was ignorant of Mr. Jay's departure for America; desires that the packet may be opened by the gentleman who transacts Mr. Jay's business and the information contained therein acted upon. Returns to England the following Monday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 28; A.D.S. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Agreement in adjustment of accounts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 30; A.L.S. 4p.; Alexander, William. Richmond, Va
    Concerning his journey to Philadelphia, his high opinion of that city and the marks of kindness he received from Franklin's family. Account of his business; his decision to settle at Richmond for the present; prospect of Norfolk becoming a great mart; his meeting with the noteworthy men of Virginia. Franklin's old colleague, Arthur Lee, has been sent to treat with the Indians. Hopes his boy gives satisfaction to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Frisi, Paolo. Milan
    Has followed in the newspapers the great events so closely connected with Franklin. Takes this opportunity to introduce le Chevalier Castiglio, a member of one of the most distinguished Milanese families, who proposes making a tour in America, in order to study that brave nation more closely and also to continue his researches in Natural History.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May 31; A.L.S. 4p.; Houdetot, Comtesse d'
    Begging for news of Franklin; describes in detail the easiest way for him to make the journey to Sannois, where she awaits his visit with the greatest pleasure; will be delighted also to receive his two grandsons.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1784. May ?]; L. 3p.; de la Mothe Cadillac, Marie Thérèse
    Petitions Franklin to help her secure possession of lands granted to her grandfather in the territory of Massachusetts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 May; A.L.S. 3p.; Walter, John. London
    Acknowledging Franklin's kind letter and the present accompanying it. Concerning his new method of printing as contained in the pamphlet sent Franklin; will open his new printing-house on the first day of June; minute description of the arrangement on which the facility of the work depends; would be glad to have his improvement laid before the Court of France and would willingly send the King a complete printing fount, trusting only to that monarch's liberality.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Huguet, ------. Paris
    Is informed that Franklin sends persons to Russia to cultivate land there; begs Franklin to grant him a tract to land to clear and cultivate.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Thompson, Thomas. Dover
    Informing him of the departure of Mr. [John] Jay and family on the ship "Edward"; their inability to carry with them the picture of the Marquis de la Fayette, intended for General Washington; asks instructions as to its further disposition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Announcing his intended departure for l'Orient on the 22nd inst.; puts himself at Franklin's service. News received lately from America; great debates occasioned by the Cincinnati affair; intention of Congress to adjourn; the "Washington" packet offered for sale.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779] June 4; A.L. 3p.; Brillon, Mme
    Tells Franklin of unhappiness in her home life, attributes it in great part to disparity of age, her husband being twenty-four years older than she. Laments the fact that young girls in France are often married to men much older than themselves because both parties happen to have about the same of worldly goods.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Nov., 1906, 172.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Laurens, Henry. London
    Introducing a son of John Parker, Esq., of South Carolina, who is studying law; expects to spend his next vacation in Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Fanning, James. Angers
    Enclosing a memorial [2 p.] setting forth his claim to certain lands in Florida, and desires to send a letter of attorney to have possession taken of them; begs Franklin to certify to his being a French subject.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Dutartre, Melin. L'Arbatetre
    Sends a request from the Principal of an Irish College. Impossibility of her visiting "her dear Papa"; asks if it is equally impracticable for Franklin to visit her; begs for a good English letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 7; A.L.S. 1p.; C. Drogart and Co. Paris
    Asking him to certify to certain signatures on a power of attorney which must be transmitted to Boston immediately.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Forster's Brothers. Bordeaux
    Sending the enclosed letter received from "R. F." by ship from Dublin and requesting an answer through their hands. Their offer to serve Franklin with wines; their hope in the future to open an extensive connection with their friends, Messrs. Bache and Shee.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Valazé, Charles Eléonor Dufriche de
    Monsieur, the King's brother, is anxious to hear of the success of the writer's book in America; he is still in ignorance of whether it has ever been forwarded to Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Rosehill ?, -----. Rouen
    Received Franklin's obliging information concerning his son; desires the names of any Virginia gentlemen of note at present in Paris; has a very considerable interest in New Jersey; hopes to wait on Franklin in July.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Lacroix, ----- de.
    Reduced by shipwreck to a state of misery; is the inventor of a plan for the welfare of humanity, which he is unable to carry out from lack of means; begs Franklin to assist him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Bridgen, Edward
    Forwards the accompanying book at the request of Mr. [Richard] Champion. Departure for New York of their mutual friends Mr. [Henry] Laurens and his son.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Laubarède, ----- de
    Repeating his request for a few louis d'or.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 12; L.S. 1p.; George Clinton and James Duane. New York
    Introducing Lieut.-Col. [Matthew] Clarkson, whose business in Europe is to solicit donations for the University of the State of New York; have instructed him to consult with Franklin on the best mode of accomplishing his mission.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Nekrep, Abbé J. Vienna
    Acknowleding his politeness to him at Passy. Description of a balloon experiment at Vienna.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Vicq d' Azyr, Félix
    Sends him the report of Messrs. Andry and Thouret on the magnets of l'Abbé Le Noble. The Royal Society of Medicine extremely flattered by Franklin's request for a collection of their volumes; will forward him the ones already printed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Witherspoon, Jno. London
    Introducing Mr. William Brown who has been a teacher in London and who goes to Paris to perfect his knowledge and pronunciation of the French language; if Franklin could procure him a position where he might teach English or the classics, it would be a true charity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Valazé, Charles Eléonor Dufriche de
    Introducing his nephew, M. Dufriche Des Genettes, who has studied medicine for four years in Paris, and now goes to England to learn the methods in vogue there; begs letters of recommendation for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 16; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bailly, Jean Sylvain
    Requests the return of the original registry or record book of the Commission, as it is to be copied.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 17; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bailly, Jean Sylvain. Chaillot
    The Commissioners [to investigate mesmerism] will wait upon him Saturday, before noon; they are Messrs. Majault, Sallin, Guillotin, D'Arcet, physicians; Messrs. Le Roy, de Bory, and Bailly, academicians; they will bring also M. [Charles] Deslon, and the young man who has already been the subject of an experiment, as well as Mesdames de Bory, de Romagni and de Moret.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Bridgen, Edward
    Concerning the last five volumes of the Royal Society's Transactions, which he hopes by this time have arrived safely. Good wishes from himself and wife.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Roubaud, -----. Aix
    Pained by the want of accuracy displayed by the public papers; the United States of America is constantly referred to as the Thirteen United States in spite of the fact that Vermont was the fourteenth state to be admitted to the Union; appeals to Franklin to set the matter right.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Jefferson, Thomas. Boston
    Expected Congress to communicate to Franklin directly the powers committed to him, [John] Adams and himself. Expects to sail for France in July. His desire to meet with [John] Jay before his departure for America. News of Mrs. [Richard] Bache and her family.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 102; Bigelow, VIII, 505).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 19; A.L.S. 1p.; du Petit-Vendin, —. Arras
    Begs for information of his son, Louis de Maresquelle, Colonel of Artillery and Inspector-General of the foundries at Boston; no word received from him since 1781.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Roux, -----. Paris
    M. Court de Gebelin, who has just died, honored him with his friendship. Introduces a Swiss, a man of letters, who expected to get a position in Paris through the kindness of M. de Gebelin, but his death has left him without resources; begs Franklin's aid.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Bache, Richard. Philadelphia
    A long time since they have heard from Franklin; their hopes of seeing him at home that summer, especially if it be true that Congress has slighted a late application of his, in spite of its meeting with general approval; powerful influence of Mr. J[ohn] A[dams] with some Congressional members. Dr. Franklin's letters to Dr. [Samuel] Cooper; the possibility of the Doctor's death preventing the letters from being made as public as Franklin wished; advisability of transmitting copies to some other friend in Boston. News of the family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Bache, Richard. Philadelphia
    Introducing to Franklin's notice and civility, Mr. Francis West, eldest son of the late Mr. William West of Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Bache, Richard. Philadelphia
    Introducing his worthy friend, Mr. John Donaldson, of Philadelphia, a merchant of excellent character and reputation. Cannot help flattering himself that they shall have Franklin with them that summer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Rati, Joseph. Genoa
    Finds that the American flag is not respected by the Moors of Barbary; is afraid to return to New England with his rich cargo, in a ship only fit for a peaceable trade; has heard much talk of a pass granted by the French Court to American vessels trading in the straits; encloses a copy of his register [1 p.] to prove his vessel an American possession; if his request is refused, will be obliged to make his vessel a British bottom; begs Franklin's advice and direction.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 June 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Bridgen, Edward